A Guide to the Augusta County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1746-1912
Library of Virginia
- 1857-068: Admr. of Joseph Jamison vs. Maria L. Jamison (alias Mariah L. Jamison) etc.
  After the death of her husband, Maria Jamison struggles to provide income for her family. The suit is a request to sell property so that the dower may be restored to Maria and so that she can move the family closer to town to make her sewing business more profitable. The case provides an interesting account of a woman struggling to manage an estate/farm and to support her family.
- 1857-082: Recv(s) of Nicholas C. Kinney, etc. vs. Admr. of Jeremiah Aude, etc.
  Aude emigrated to the U.S. from Great Britain and became a U.S. citizen. He owned a substantial amount of real and personal estate in Augusta County. Aude died without a will. He had no wife or children. All his relatives lived in Great Britain. They made claims to his property in U.S. Problems - a) It was unlawful in the U.S. for aliens to inherit property unless they declared to be citizens of the U.S. They all stated they would become U.S. citizens. b) To receive their portion of Aude's estate, they had to prove they were kin to Aude. Exhibits filed in the suit include numerous certificates of burials, marriages, and baptisms copied from church registers in England going back to the 1700's. Also included is a genealogical chart illustrating their relationship to Aude.
- 1858-042: Alexander S. Hall vs. James F. Patterson, etc.
  References to a suit vs. US Government related to US Revolutionary War service of Henry W. Nicholson, cornet of cavalry in VA Line.
- 1859-006: Patrick McAlear vs. Admr of Charles McAlear, etc.
  Contains naturalization papers of Michael McAleer of Ireland, 1843 Rockbridge Co.
- 1860-016: James W. Bishop, etc. vs. Admr. of Elizabeth P. Via and Exr. of Elizabeth P. Via vs. James W. Bishop, etc.
  Heirs sued to overturn will of Via who freed all of her slaves and left 4000 dollars to send them to a free state. Will was upheld. Receipts and extensive account documenting executor's trip to Columbus, Ohio in 1861 with freed slaves including purchase for them of a farm and household goods. Also includes names, ages, and physical description of each slave.
- 1860-041: Daniel McCune (alias Daniel Boyer), etc. vs. William Craig, etc.
  Freed slaves of Samuel McCune were left money from sale of his goods and property in 1835 and moved to Ohio. Agent to infants William Craig being sued by now-adult infants Daniel and Gilbert McCune, former slaves, for not doing his job properly. Big question of the suit seems to be question of court jurisdiction to decide the case. Suit dismissed due to lack of activity.
- 1863-027: Exr. of Chapman J. Stuart vs. Mary J. Stuart (alias Mary Jane Clark)
  Case pertains to the disbursements of the estates of Chapman Stuart and his father Alexander Stuart. Mary Stuart was the infant daughter of Chapman who was seeking more funds as she became of an age to go about in society. There is a great amount of documentation on the expenses and purchases of a young woman during the period, which includes biannual account ledgers of her purchases for the years 1860 to 1862. The executor Archibald H. H. Stuart explains why there is not as much money in the estate as her father had originally thought when he composed the will, and he includes receipts showing how the estate is being funded. Included in the case are receipts signed by J.E.B. Stuart for funds that were allotted for his education at West Point. There is also information on slave property with several slaves mentioned by name.
- 1867-021: Pamelia Jones vs. Admr. of Armestead Jones
  Pamelia, a free woman of color, sues her brother's widow, whom she accuses of being of unsound mind, for control of his estate. Mention is made of their mother Mary Jones who was once a slave.
- 1867-054: Rebecca Ann Vickers vs. George Vickers
  Rebecca Ann Vickers, freeborn, married her first husband George Washington, a slave who went over to fight with the Union and was later presumed dead. Subsequently Rebecca Ann married George Vickers under the agreement that she would return to her first husband if he should prove to be still alive. After having children with her second husband, Rebecca Ann did return to her first husband when he reappeared in Augusta Co.
- 1868-010: George Coiner vs. Dinah Coiner and 1868-015: Diana Kiner vs. George Kiner
  George, a freedman, sued for divorce on grounds that he was forced into marriage with Dinah Bumgardner. George's bill includes a story of being apprehended by two military guards, one black and one white, and forced to Staunton. There he was given the choice of marrying said Dinah or being taken to Richmond as a prisoner. After being reassured by an officer that he could leave after the ceremony, George entered into the ceremony at bayonet point. There is an implication in the bill that Dinah's employer Strouse was involved in the case, and he in fact provided a deposition in her favor. Dinah claims that George promised to marry her and then had "carnal knowledge" of her. After the ceremony, George claims that he never cohabitated with the defendant.
- 1869-005: Thomas Bell vs. Mary Bell
  Includes interesting material on what is like to be married while a slave, including the discussion of the deaths of two of their children while the third was sold to another plantation. Thomas discusses his former owner Blackwood who he continued to be employed by after the war. Thomas also briefly worked with the Freedmen's Bureau; although, no real information is provided.
- 1870-002: Jonathan Landes vs. Robert A. Curry and wife
  Landes, who describes himself as being of "advanced age," was still considered to be of military age and was afraid of conscription into the Confederate army. Landes listed being allegiant to the United States as one of the reasons that he hired sixteen-year-old George H. Curry to be his substitute. Landes agreed to a series of payments amounting to $850 to be paid through the year 1866 to George Curry or his mother. George Curry died during the war and his parents took up a suit on his behalf and sued Landes successfully for the money owed to them according to the contract. Landes appeals that ruling in this chancery suit by claiming that the contract was illegal because it served to further the rebellious cause of the confederacy. The judge disagreed and claimed that the contract was a personal one and not subject to the outcome of the war.
- 1870-026: Mary Frances Kinney vs. William H. Tams etc.
  Case concerns a marriage settlement for Mary in which most of her property remained in her control; although the actual control of the money and property was maintained by her uncle. Mary is suing because her uncle invested most of her money in Confederate bonds and stocks without her knowledge. Case includes an interesting deposition of Mary in which is discussed the relationship of women and business.
- 1870-067: Jordan and Peyton vs. Mrs. Sally G. Dyer and Mrs. Sally G. Dyer vs. Jordan and Peyton
  Dyer hired out three slaves. Slave Fanny was sent to a second hire, of which Mrs. Dyer claimed no knowledge or consent. Her new owner Mason was given "occasion to correct her ... for some fault," and the slave Fanny ran off back to her home with Dyer. Dyer refused to return Fanny to Mason who she claimed "had given her a very severe whipping for some alleged fault." Dyer said that Fanny returned to her after being "cruelly beaten" and "lodged in jail."
- 1876-058: John J. Rusmisel etc. vs. Exr. of Christian Rusmisel etc.
  John J. Rusmisel served in the 25th VA Infantry (Heck's Regiment); POW at Ft. Delaware (per bill); includes (as an exhibit) letter from John J. Rusmisel to his brother (written from battlefield-Orange County, VA, 1 April 1864); mentions that Grant has taken over Union Forces. Image numbers 252-253
- 1876-115: Archibald J. Porter etc. vs. Archibald D. Trotter etc. and Archibald J. Porter etc. vs. David S. Young etc.
  Land dispute involving Methodist Episcopal Church of Staunton and Methodist Episcopal Church South; dispute covers sale of land containing church building. One of the defendants is Mary J. Baldwin (for whom Mary Baldwin College, formerly Augusta Female Seminary, is named.)
- 1877-029: John Pelter, etc. vs. Exr. of Sampson Pelter, etc.
  Plaintiffs are former slaves (who have taken Pelter's name); dispute over land bequeathed to the plaintiffs. Argument includes fact that Sampson Pelter died after Civil War was over, and plaintiffs had been freed.
- 1877-071: Erasmus Stribling Crawford, etc. vs. Exx. of James Crawford, etc. and Margaret A. Crawford vs. Admr. of Nicholas K. Trout, etc.
  Causes mention a slave named Matilda, owned by the late James Crawford, who was hired out to the Western State Asylum. Includes a copy of Matilda's bill of sale between Thomas Stribling and James Crawford, 5 December 1825.
- 1879-094: Heirs of Silas Henton vs. Heirs of Silas Henton; Admr. of Rachael Adeline Reamer, etc. vs. Admr. of William S. Henton; Admr. of Rachael Adeline Reamer, etc. vs. David B. Henton, etc.; Lewis M. McClung and wife, etc. vs. David B. Henton, etc.
  Includes depositions of former slaves, who had been owned by the Henton and Reamer families. Also includes report of sale of Silas Henton's slaves.
- 1879-042: Heirs of Jacob Dull vs. Admr. of Jacob Dull etc.; John Pery vs. Admr. of Jacob Dull, etc.; John B. Hanger vs. Admr. of Jacob Dull, etc.
  Case includes a genealogical chart of the heirs of Jacob Dull (who died unmarried with no living children). Image number 1765
- 1880-035: John M. Ryan, etc. vs. John F. Hix, etc.
  Case includes personal correspondence between John Hix (Ironton, OH) and Annie E. Ryan (Staunton, VA) who were cousins. Hix found her by writing to the superintendent of the lunatic asylum. Hix had lost all contact with his family (even though his sister lived in Huntington, WV, about 20 miles away). Much of the content involves the estate of Aunt Sallie (or Sally) Ryan and distribution of funds from the sale of her property.
- 1880-119: Wesleyan Female Institute vs. John H. Plunkett, etc.
  Case includes two architectural drawings, showing a building addition that Plunkett and others were charged with building.
- 1884-084: John M. Brown and wife vs. Philip O. Palmer, etc. and Admr. of Philip O. Palmer, etc. vs. Foutz and wife
  John M. Brown and his wife Clara C. Brown nee Lamb sue Philip Palmer who was her guardian and controller of her father's estate. Brown alleges that Palmer misappropriated the funds and did not care for Clara properly. Several depositions in the case discuss Clara's role in the family and work done by women. Also include are eight fabric swatches entered as an exhibit for the deposition of Catharine Ott. Ott states that they are fabric samples from eight Sunday dress owned by Clara Lamb.
- 1887-069: William Spears vs. Martha Spears
  Plaintiff and defendant were former slaves, whose marriage was validated by the Act of the [General] Assembly of the 27th of February 1866. Defendant packed all the plaintiff's belongings into a hired coach while he was at work and deserted him and their children.
- 1889-026: Richard Watkins, etc. vs. Laflin and Rand Powder Co., etc.
  Plaintiffs filed for injunction against the Laflin and Rand Powder Co., which was trying to build a powder magazine near their houses (three others were in existence, in some cases closer than the one proposed). Laflin and Rand was the number 2 producer of explosive powder, behind the DuPont Company, which later acquired it. Both were part of the "powder trust," broken up by Theodore Roosevelt in the early 20th Century. Includes a letter from the Repauno Chemical Company (manufacturer of Atlas powder) explaining how safe (as compared to black powder) its product is.
- 1889-042: Robert Knightly vs. City of Staunton
  The City of Staunton purchased land upstream from the plaintiff and diverted the streams that flowed through both (both pieces of property were purchased from the same family). The plaintiff claimed that this destroyed the value of his property because there was not enough water to power mills and other things. After he filed suit, the city condemned the section of his property through which the stream ran.
- 1893-078: Annie Davis vs. William Davis
  Divorce case in which the defendant left his wife after about 4 years of marriage for her mother (the husband and mother had one child after that).
- 1895-023: Hugh F. Lyle, etc vs. Mervin E. Kyle
  The defendant built a slaughterhouse and stockyard very near plaintiffs' house (bill gives exact distances), polluting a stream and causing insufferable smells and noises.
- 1895-048: Ann Blackburn vs. Exr. of Samuel Blackburn, etc.
  Case involves the estate of General Samuel Blackburn, and Revolutionary War general. He was the son in law of General George Mathews, also a Revolutionary War veteran and later governor of Georgia (resigned after the Yazoo Land Fraud)
- 1900-054: Annie B. Back vs. John B. Back
  Marriage license was obtained in the bride's absence (per bill)-groom claimed that she was 20 years old, when she was in fact 13. She had run away from her adopted father's house, where the couple returned a few days after the marriage. The defendant abandoned the plaintiff after about two months of marriage.
- 1903-091: J.H. Headen, etc. vs. County School Board of Augusta County
  Plaintiffs brought suit to stop the county school board from closing and selling two public schools. Much of the argument involves the fact that the students would have to travel over a busy bridge (or railroad bridge) to get to their new school.